# Ao LIU

# Ph.D. in Computer Science

Research Software Engineer at Google
☐ +1 (518) 233-4797
☐ aoliu.cs@gmail.com
☐ aoliu-cs.github.io

# Summary

Research Machine Learning (Recommendation Systems, Learning to Rank, Algorithm Design, etc.),

Interests Differential Privacy, Computational Social Choice, and Quantum Computation

**Experience** 1+ years of industry experience in personalization, recommendation systems, LLM, theoretical computer science, differential privacy, learning to rank, and adversarial robustness

**Academic** Published 20+ papers, filed 2 patents, and received 250+ citations to date. Reviewed 50+ papers for top AI conferences or journals.

#### Education

1/2018 – 5/2023 **Ph.D.** in **Computer Science**, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI) Troy, NY Thesis: *Group Decision Makings from Partial Preferences* [Link]

8/2015-5/2018 M.Eng. in Material Engineering, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI) Troy, NY Focus on optics and polymer physics, received Presidential Graduate Research Fellowship

8/2010-5/2014 **B.S.** in **Mathematics and Physics**, Tsinghua University Beijing, China *Minor in Computer Technology*, and *in Academic Talent Program* 

# Experience

7/2023–Present Research Software Engineer at Google Core ML Mountain View, CA
Design and Research More Efficient Transformers for Recommendation Systems

5/2022 - 8/2022 Research Intern at Google Core ML Mountain View, CA

Project: Unbiased Learning to Rank with a More Accurate Position Bias Estimator

- O Significantly more accurate ( $\sim 6\%$ ) on predictions v.s. state-of-the-art without any cost
- Proposed a novel probabilistic model to more accurately estimate position bias and designed an unbiased recommendation system based on it.
- Implemented the data pipeline and machine learning algorithm for the proposed unbiased recommendation system. Integrated all into Google codebase. (Python, TensorFlow, C/C++)

#### 5/2019-8/2019 Visiting Scholar at MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab

Cambridge, MA

and 9/2018-1/2019 Project: Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Differential Privacy

- 9/2018-1/2019 O Delivered one academic paper (on top AI journal and conference) and two patents.
  - O Significantly more robust ( $\sim$ 12%) and more accurate v.s. state-of-the-art without any cost. Note that we improved two trade-off properties at the same time.
  - O Designed the first-ever algorithm with theoretically guaranteed top-k robustness against  $\ell_{\infty}$ -norm attacks, where the theoretical proofs use Rényi differential privacy.
  - Implemented the proposed robust algorithm and tested its robustness, accuracy, and computational
    efficiency on various tasks, including neural network interpretation, image classification, and
    objective detection. (PyTorch, TorchRay, TensorFlow, MATLAB)

### Skills

Coding Python, C/C++, TensorFlow, PyTorch, TorchRay, MATLAB, LATEX

Design & Algorithm design, Time & Sample-complexity analysis, User-modeling, MCMC, Statistics, Theory Privacy analysis, Robustness analysis, Model identifiability, Smoothed analysis

### Review Services

Journal Information Sciences, ACM ToIS, TMLR, DMLR, Sankhya B

Conference NeurIPS (20, 21, 22, 23, & 24), ICML (22, 23 & 24), ICLR (23 & 24), AAAI (21 & 22), IJCAI-22

	Selected Publications
TMLR	Smoothed Differential Privacy [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Yu-Xiang Wang, and Lirong Xia
UAI-23	Accelerating Voting by Quantum Computation [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Qishen Han, Lirong Xia, and Nengkun Yu
AIJ and $AAAI$ -23 (oral)	Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Differential Privacy [Link] [ArXiv] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Xiaoyu Chen, Sijia Liu, Lirong Xia, and Chuang Gan
AAAI-22	The Semi-Random Likelihood of Doctrinal Paradoxes [PDF] $\underline{Ao\ Liu}$ and Lirong Xia
UAI-20 (oral)	How Private Are Commonly-Used Voting Rules? [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Yun Lu, Lirong Xia, and Vassilis Zikas
AAAI-19 (oral)	Near-Neighbor Methods in Random Preference Completion [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Qiong Wu, Zhenming Liu, and Lirong Xia
AAAI-19 (oral)	Learning Plackett-Luce Mixture from Partial Preferences [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Zhibing Zhao, Chao Liao, Pinyan Lu, and Lirong Xia
ETRA-19 (oral)	Differential Privacy for Eye-Tracking Data [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Andrew Duchowski, Reynold Bailey, Kenneth Holmqvist, and Eakta Jain
AAAI-23 (oral)	Differentially Private Condorcet Voting [PDF] Zhechen Li, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Yongzhi Cao, and Hanpin Wang
IJCAI-22 (oral)	Learning Mixtures of Random Utility Models with Features from Incomplete Preferences Zhibing Zhao, $\underline{Ao\ Liu}$ , and Lirong Xia [PDF]
JAIR and IJCAI-23 (oral)	Learning to Design Fair and Private Voting Rules [PDF] Farhad Mohsin, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Pin-Yu Chen, Francesca Rossi, and Lirong Xia
	Let It Snow: Adding Pixel Noise to Protect the Users Identity [Link] Brendan John, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Sanjeev Koppal, and Eakta Jain
<del>-</del>	Simulation of Pulse Responses of Lithium Salt-Doped Poly-Ethyleneoxide [Link] <u>Ao Liu</u> , F. Zeng, Y. Hu, S. Lu, W. Dong, X. Li, C. Chang, and D. Guo
	$ ightharpoonup View \ All \ Publications \ at \ [Personal \ Website] \ [Google \ Scholar]$
	Patents
US 11687777 B2	Certifiably Robust Interpretation [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Sijia Liu, Bo Wu, Lirong Xia, Qi Cheng Li, and Chuang Gan
US 11341598 B2	Interpretation Maps with Guaranteed Robustness [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Sijia Liu, Abhishek Bhandwaldar, Chuang Gan, Lirong Xia, and Qi Cheng Li
	Awards and Teaching
9/2019 - 5/2022	RPI-IBM AI Horizon Scholarship
9/2016 - 5/2017	RPI Presidential Graduate Research Fellowship [Certificate]
1/2023 - 5/2023	Teaching Assistant of CSCI 4150: Introduction to AI
9/2017 - 1/2018	Teaching Assistant of MATH 1020: Calculus II
4/2021	Guest Lecture at CSCI 4967/6967: Economics and Computation